hey guys welcome out cory here yet again
we're we're doing design stuff today
we're gonna be covering
five mistakes that i run into when it
comes to designs and screen printing and
we're gonna be covering how to avoid
them and how to fix them
hey guys i missed you
i feel like i haven't seen you in a
while i haven't been out over here
talking with you but today uh
i got some some uh tips and tricks and
uh some know know-how and some do's and
don'ts with or without the scooter stick
it's all in the realm of screen printing
design i
uh over here at golden press studio and
the
lead art director
that's what they call me
i manage uh everything that all the
artwork all that kind of stuff that
comes into the studio i'm the one that
preps it and gets it ready to be printed
on shirts and all that stuff over the
years i've uh noticed a handful of
reoccurring issues that
just show up all the time i want to
cover some of those with you guys how to
fix them how to avoid them maybe you're
not a designer and you're trying to get
shirts printed for the very first time
and so maybe these are some things to
keep in mind when you're
sending artwork to any other screen
printer that these are going to be
helpful things that they're going to
appreciate if you maybe do some of these
steps so the first thing you just need
to know when it comes to screen printing
design is you're going to want to be
working in adobe illustrator or another
vector-based program a vector is sort of
a mathematical equation that doesn't
matter how large you uh kind of stretch
your design or how small you shrink your
design down it's always gonna have
perfect resolution and when it comes to
screen printing we want our artwork as
crisp and as clean as possible so
without any uh further into doing let's
just uh
jump into tip number one
expand your fonts
so let me show you a little example of
what it looks like when someone doesn't
expand their fonts and what what prompt
you end up getting so
this is a file that someone sent over in
the past and if i open it with adobe
illustrator i get this
right here this is missing fonts
and uh
sometimes illustrator can do a little
search and can find some fonts for you
and then you might be able to get lucky
on that
but let's just hit close and skip and
just close this file let me show you how
to go about expanding fonts if uh
if you're the one making this artwork
you know getting that prompt pretty much
the next step for you is just to contact
whoever created this file and ask them
to expand it or send you the font and
then you can just install it and that
will fix the problem but i'll show you
real quick on how to go about
expanding fonts just in general and so
we have this font right here and it has
this little underline on it there's no
outline around each of these because it
is a font
and we want to turn it into a shape
instead of just being a font we wanted a
shape so everyone can use this and work
with it on any computer we have our font
selected we're going to go up to object
we're going to go down to expand
click
it's going to say fill have object and
fill checked you're just going to hit
okay and boom
now we have all these little anchor
points and this is now a shape
instead of just a font and uh it's a
vectored object we can you know zoom in
as close as we want and it's always
going to stay super crisp
we can make it big or small and
this is what we're looking for when
we're working with a design getting
ready to screen print just a nice
expanded font and again the reason why
we're doing this is when it's a font if
some other person that's opening this
file doesn't have that font pre-loaded
into their computer
then they can't open it that's why you
got that prompt before
but
if you expand your font and make it a
shape then any person can open this file
and it's just being read as a shape it's
not a font they don't need anything
preloaded into their computer
they're able to just grab this
go and there won't be any issues tip
number two
is very similar
to uh
the old expand our font but we're
talking about expanding our stroke and
say uh someone you know they made this
design
and this is exactly the size of
of the circle they wanted this is the
width of the stroke they wanted on this
here circle maybe they didn't make this
design to scale of what they're actually
going to print it as
and so here i am in illustrator and i'm
gonna you know prep this artwork and so
i'd highlight this circle and i'm like
okay
uh i need this circle to be
uh maybe 10 inches wide
and so i'm just gonna you know set it
off to the edge i need to pull it over
this 10
and we see the width of this circle
right now but as i make it bigger and
bigger and bigger and bigger
now
it's it's not the same it's kind of
changed its its shape and so if i
command z
and command c
and v copy a new one and i'm gonna go
and hit object and expand
say okay
when i expand this circle it's going to
maintain its width contrary to this one
here let's give it a different color
just to
to help show you what's going on
and when i
oh it's kind of behind it at the moment
but when i put this one at 10 inches
and let's bring it forward you can see
that they're clearly different
sizes
uh and that's what we don't want we
don't want uh to switch up a
design or change it
we want to maintain exactly its shape
now i believe there is a setting within
illustrator that you can go
and uh set and change that i think your
strokes can maintain their shape and
size i prefer to work with shapes pretty
much every time i'm working in
illustrator i like the final product to
always just be solid shape
just because strokes and those kind of
things can get hairy at times maybe
you're dealing with a stroke
that has some kind of unique width to it
say you have a stroke that's kind of
like this
and you can select this and if you go up
to object you can't hit expand it's
grayed out but if you hit expand
appearance
then that turns it into a shape again
and so now this is a shape versus a
stroke like it was before i'll just kind
of show you we'll compare contrast yet
again we go object expand appearance so
this one is a shape this one is a stroke
but if we grab both of these and maybe
we'll scale them down
you can see
what happens
that we don't want that happening we
don't want it to get all fat and weird
we want it to maintain its actual shape
alright so the third kind of tip i have
for you this one's a little personal and
for me so if you disagree with it
whatever i strongly feel that you should
not use clipping masks in adobe
illustrator
and that's pertaining to
screen printing design you know i think
in other realms of design it's probably
fine i've used clipping masks in the
past for non-screen printed designs but
if we're talking about screen printing i
think clipping masks often will cause
problems and they're confusing let me
show you what i'm talking about say
someone sent you a design they want this
circle with this texture
printed on a shirt and you're like all
right cool uh you know we can do that
it's a i can zoom in it looks clearly a
vectored object i think we're running
uh in a good direction you know it's red
right now and i want to make this black
and as you can see as i my mouse is
hovering over here we have all these
little uh things that i'm i'm hovering
on
uh and that is because this is a
clipping mask and so you click on it and
you're like well it looks like a circle
and you're kind of confused because you
can't access any of these anchor points
this is what happens uh when you release
a clipping mask and so maybe maybe you
have a clipping mask and you don't
really know what to do with it so you're
gonna click you're gonna do a right
click and there's this button right here
that says release clipping mask and when
you do that things are going to go nuts
you're going to hit that and bam now all
of a sudden your design has fallen apart
you lost your circle you don't know
what's going on
and you just wanted to change the color
to black
you know so let's uh command z a couple
times and like say if i didn't take that
step i go click on this and i go to
change this to black
also now we have a black circle and it's
all messed up yeah we're in a problem
this design is completely possible to
make without using a clipping mask uh
and i'm going to show you real quick on
how to go about doing something like
this or either maybe you have to fix
this artwork or maybe
you just avoided using the clipping mask
and did this method from the start and
that's going to save everyone kind of a
bit of a headache
so
let's go and just drag
this copy off to the side just so we
have our reference or our main original
design
and we are going to release this
clipping mask
and uh we still actually have our circle
it's kind of hidden in there and we'll
just fill that in
and so what i'm going to do
is i'm going to hit the letter m and
draw a big box over top of everything
and let's maybe layer it down a little
bit
just so i can get to that circle
now we're at our circle and we're going
to grab the big box as well
and i'm going to go to our pathfinder
i'm going to hit minus front and now
i've punched a hole
uh in this big box that i've created so
all i have to do now is click on this
texture and this is a compound path we
can see up here and it is underneath
this black
kind of shape that we've now created so
click on that i click on that shape
and both are compound paths and i'm
going gonna hit minus front on the
pathfinder
and then
boom we've punched out our design
and
it has the spherical edge just like this
other one
but without the whole clipping mask
issue and i can click on this i can
change its color no problem
and uh
yeah i'm good to go and that's sort of
how you can
manage a clipping mask kind of solve
that clippy mask problem
and ultimately again i recommend not
using them if you're dealing with screen
printing designing just take the proper
steps to make your
file that you're working with just a
solid shape
and it's really not that challenging if
you just think ahead all right so tip
number four
is know how many colors the screen
printer you're using can print this is
something that i run into a lot of times
where
a client reaches out to us and they have
their design all put together and they
send it over to us i have to respond
back to them saying hey our press that
we use
its maximum color is six colors that's
the most colors we can do in a design
then i have to ask them hey is there any
way that you can uh
lessen the amount of colors that you're
using before you start designing it's a
good thing to know all right how many
colors can my printer work with and you
won't have to deal with having to rework
your design over and over and over again
and i just want to show you guys a quick
example of
something that i had to do to kind of
solve some issues with with the design
that someone sent over to us a while
back so let's hop back into illustrator
i'll just show you that this is a really
cool design that a client sent over to
us and over here is the original design
and uh
as you can see looks awesome a lot of
colors going on a lot of different
things
and honestly if you count color for
color all together i think it's around
12 colors
and like i said earlier our shop can
only print six colors and so you know we
have you know we have this tone right
here
uh and then this type of tan we have
like kind of two different tans we have
the skin tone up here then we have the
shadow of the skin tone you know we got
a lot of stuff going on really really
cool but it's about 12 colors and and
not a lot of shops uh run 12 color
presses over here and i had to like work
back and forth with the client uh to
dial this in but this is what i ended up
coming up with and this is actually now
just
a six color print
and how i actually did it a lot of like
that these shadow colors i ended up
using half tones that
i put together in photoshop and then had
to bring it over here but
and even the hair had to get a little
creative i ended up using uh this uh
this color as more of like the underbase
of the hair and then uh doing a bunch of
half toning going on in there uh kind of
a different density of halftone to
create that and actually when it when it
did end up printing it it looked
actually a lot closer to this brown tone
this is a great example of like hey they
sent over
a 12 color print and we were actually
able to break it down into a six color
and
if uh you know the the people designing
this would have known that beforehand i
think that you know we could have easily
saved a lot of this process and and so
that's just kind of my tip to you is
when you're jumping into designing uh
screen printed artwork just uh shoot a
shoot a call over or a text over to your
screen printer you're going to be
working with yeah just see hey how many
colors is the maximum that we can use in
a design and i'm they're always happy to
let you know and it'll just save uh
save your butt and save your head tip
number five give screen printers high
resolution artwork preferably vectored
images this is something that if you're
in screen printing you've ran into this
problem over and over again they send
you a file and it is pixelated and gross
not a vector file probably a jpeg or a
png or something like that i can't work
with this i can't use this who designed
this can you reach out to the original
artist and maybe they have a vector file
if uh there's not a vector file at all
it just blows my mind i'm like you're a
large company you don't have a vector
file of your logo this is your logo i
don't know have vector files of your
logos say there's nothing that can be
done
uh i'm gonna kind of show you you know
how to work with this stuff we have this
little leaf logo and as you can see
look at these jagged lines it's also a
png it's a rasterized image that looks
real bad i got a couple different
techniques you guys can use
to go and fix this step one you can just
click on your your uh little png you can
go over here and lock that layer and hit
p on your keyboard grab the pen tool and
you can just
straight use that pen tool and just kind
of
anchor point this whole thing out and so
as you can see uh you know this this
works and it's an option something i do
honestly a lot that's a bit quicker i
don't use it for every single design but
maybe they just send you something that
can work well with this and so if you
have an ipad and an apple pencil and the
program procreate i'm going to show you
a kind of quick and simple technique to
maybe up the quality of a kind of
pixelated bad graphic so the first thing
i'm going to do is i go to this little
plus sign up here i'm going to click on
it and let's just make a new canvas
and uh let's just say 5 000
by 5 000
uh
dpi is 500 so we're working with a very
large file right here it's got it allows
us 17 layers so let's just create this
and
we're going to hit the little wrench up
here we're going to say insert a photo
and insert our little leaf graphic as
you can see it's very very small
and so we're gonna scale it up a bit
and uh you know this is our problem we
have all these jagged pixelly lines
and uh we're just gonna kind of trace
over this with a nice and sharp
uh black line so we've got our black
selected we're gonna make a new layer
just make make a bunch of new layers who
cares uh
and uh we're gonna choose this tapered
black uh because it's got a nice sharp
kind of edge to it very crisp and clean
and so i'm just going to jump in and
trace out
this design real quick
[Music]
and there we go
we have our newly traced out design and
you can see like man super pixelated
super rough and we look at this and
there's a lot cleaner and sharper edge
that we're working with
so we're just going to turn off that
layer um
go to our our main one and say it's
pretty good size we're just going to go
and we're going to hit that little
wrench we're going to go to share over
here and we're just going to save it as
a jpeg
and we're gonna send that over to my
computer with airdrop all right so now
we're uh back over to the computer we
got illustrator open you know this is
our old leaf that we were messing with
but let's turn over a new leaf and uh
this is our little uh leaf we just
traced out and as you can see zoom in
and a lot sharper edges that we're
working with versus you know this crazy
pixelated dirty version we can go over
here to image trace and i have a little
uh preset that i've saved that's just
called hand done i just select it and
the settings for that is my threshold is
at
97. my paths are at 97. my corners are
97 my noise is at 1 and i have ignore
white selected we got this we got this
bounding box going on
and we're going to go up here and hit
expand
and there we go we now have a vectored
image you know we make green if we want
just like the original and you can just
see compare contrast that's terrible
this one is way more usable and you know
if you're a nice guy maybe you'll save
this uh and send it over to the client
and say here you go now you have a
vector version of your logo and you
don't have to mess around with this uh
you know dirty
pixelated version anymore one more maybe
a bonus phrase tip something maybe
you're
you know maybe not a
fluent designer
and uh you know the screen printer asked
you hey can i get you know an
illustrator file of that design that you
sent over don't
grab that same jpeg image that you sent
to them before
and then put it in an illustrator
document and hit save that's not what
they're asking for we're asking for a
vector that's what this whole thing is
about we want vector sharp clean files
so just because hey jpeg is within a
illustrator file that doesn't mean that
it's a proper illustrator file so there
you guys have it
five tips
expand your fonts
expand your strokes
maybe avoid using clipping masks know
how many colors that your screen printer
can print give us vector files for work
with high quality vector images if you
do those things your the screen printer
you're working with is going to be
really happy
i'm going to be really happy uh if
you're sending me artwork and i just
have this nice clean shape of a file
it's just like bam all i got to do click
on it make it black we're good to go
everything is great maybe you're a
designer jumping into uh designing for
screen printing do these these tips and
tricks you're going to be a better
designer and people are going to like
you more thanks for watching i hope you
learned something hopefully uh you've
subscribed to this channel because you
want knowledge you know and knowledge we
all know comes from subscriptions drop a
like we'll see you there we'll see you
in the air art on you later little
doggies arf
i feel like i've just not been
i've not done this in a while i don't
know if our viewers feel the same
[Music]
you